this is a combined two in one video that
looks at the safety of microwaves and
check out the doctor's note for recent
videos on how microwaving stacks up
against other cooking methods for
different vegetables so should we be
concerned about microwaves
watch to find out
[Music]
when people have asked me if microwave
ovens are hazardous
my typical snide response is yes
if you drop them on your foot
but it turns out that's actually a real
thing hundreds of americans end up in
the emergency room every year because a
microwave dropped on them
or they hurt their back trying to lift
one or falling onto a microwave oven i'm
not sure how that works maybe they like
tripped on it
but the majority of microwave injuries
involve scalding oneself on hot foods or
liquids
but when people go to pubmed and search
the medical literature and see all these
scary sounding titles about the hazards
of microwave ovens they may not realize
these are like articles about
jelly donuts
hazards of a microwave oven an
adolescent patient ravenously hungry
rushed home from school for his
afternoon snack found a jelly donut
popped it in the microwave the outside
was just comfortably warm and so he
gulped it down
before the searing pain started from the
burning jelly inside and he had to go to
the hospital
and that's the tricky thing about
microwave cooking you know with
conventional cooking the outside is
hotter than the inside but with
microwaving the inside can get burning
hot even while the outside remains
relatively cool
now there's still a lot more kids
getting burned from regular stoves the
injuries related to stove use vastly
exceed those associated with microwave
ovens over a five-year period about
forty thousand compared to five thousand
with microwaves and the stove burns tend
to be more severe as well
in fact you know how you're never
supposed to heat infant formula in a
microwave since you may not be able to
judge the heat of the contents just by
feeling the outside of the bottle well
if you heed that warning and use a pot
or bowl of hot water to warm it instead
you may actually end up with higher burn
risk from accidentally knocking over
scalding water so what's their solution
they suggest not warming it up at all
that's basically just a cultural thing
that we feel the need to warm it
or even better
how about not bottle feeding at all and
go for scald proof milk at perfect body
temperature
and when it comes to food whether it's a
jelly donut or jelly roll or
microwave treacle tart
or a cheese pie
basically anything that's kind of soft
in the middle can present a problem but
look
anytime there's anything liquid inside
can you just open it up let it cool
before you eat it what's the big deal
that brings us
to the case
of the exploding egg
although there are many mishaps
regarding the microwave the most
pertinent for pediatric patients seems
to be
the exploding egg
when heated in the microwave the yolk
absorbs the energy getting overheated
and pressurized both the yolk membrane
and shell
acts as a pressure barrier and any
disturbance can make it go boom
there have even been cases which the
shells have been cracked open but then
it still explodes when the yolk membrane
was pierced with a fork
and the explosion
can be so powerful and sudden that it
exceeds the blinking reflex
leaving the eyes unprotected which can
lead to vision threatening injuries
normally it's just facial burns but her
poor brother had his
face right over the plate and got his
eyes burned and ended up in the hospital
ophthalmologists should be aware of the
serious risk and caution the public
against the dangers of cooking eggs in
microwave ovens
but come on how common is this there's
all sorts of
quirky case reports in the medical
literature like
people getting eye entries from eggs
thrown around halloween or something
but if you do a search there do seem to
be a bunch of papers on exploding eggs
but i figured the best way to tell if
this was a real phenomenon would be to
search on youtube and
holy moly 25 000 videos including one
with more than a million views do not
try this at home
there's even an article in a journal on
teaching physics about how to use
microwave ovens to perform exciting
demonstrations like
spectacular egg explosions denting the
metal wall blowing the door open and
making the whole oven jump up now if if
the eggs just exploded inside that's one
thing but the problem is that it can
happen at the table you sit down to eat
them and then boom
the majority of egg injuries are to the
face eyes and nose but it can also
explode straight into your mouth then
put you in the hospital
microwave oven manufacturers evidently
specifically warn against microwaving
eggs intact and advise not only removing
the shell but piercing the yolk prior to
cooking
even reheating can be a problem she was
just carrying it in a bowl to the dining
room when it exploded rupturing her eye
causing a serious enough injury that
this group of ophthalmologists were like
look forget just putting it on in the
instruction manual maybe there should be
a warning about eggs on the microwave
itself
about 20 people a day end up in american
emergency rooms from microwave oven
related injuries a few from microwave
popcorn steam
overheated hair removal wax nearly one a
day from exploding eggs
but most are from overheated water i see
when you boil water on the stove bubbles
rise from the bottom and as they burst
the excess heat is dissipated
water heated in a microwave oven though
may not bubble and so can get even
hotter than normal boiling temperature
then if you sprinkle in some powder
tiny air bubbles are carried into the
liquid and can expand into steam bubbles
and erupt onto your hand
the fda warns to be careful when trying
to boil water in a microwave
particularly in a shiny container
or more than once or for too long or
when not letting it cool down a bit
first or when dumping something into it
most
microwave-related burns in young
children occur when their child reaches
in to grab something hot
toddlers as young as 18 months can open
a microwave so some public health
advocates have recommended that instead
of just warning people to let stuff cool
first for a few minutes there should be
some kind of like door lock that doesn't
even let you open the thing for two
minutes after it stops
which kind of undermines the whole point
of quick microwave convenience
a better idea may be to just kind of
child proof the door so you have to like
turn a knob while pressing a button to
pop the door open
when people express concerns over
microwave oven safety though they're
probably not thinking about exploding
eggs or hair wax injuries
they're concerned about the microwave
radiation itself
microwave oven manufacturers caution
people not to operate the oven with the
door open but there are you know
interlocking safety switches that should
turn it off automatically when you open
the door
unless you're stuck
inside one
i couldn't even read that article
there is some
leakage of microwave radiation though
during operation
there's this famous radio telescope
scanning the cosmos for extraterrestrial
civilizations fast radio bursts were
detected a sign of extra galactic
intelligence
nope turns out e.t was a microwave in
the staff cafeteria that the telescope
caught when it was just at the right
angle right when someone yanked the door
open
you don't need a
radio telescope to see it though a cheap
way of detecting microwave oven leakage
is to just place a computer monitor next
to the oven you can see disturbances on
the screen
or just use the microwave detector you
have in your pocket or purse right now
cell phones
look if microwaves can leak out then
they should also be able to leak in the
microwaves are actually quite similar in
size the wavelengths
though obviously different intensity
between microwave ovens and cell phones
so stick your phone in the microwave do
not turn the microwave on
but close the door and see if you can
call it
when you hear it ringing that's
confirmation that microwave type
radiation can leak in and out
and indeed you can just
directly measure the leakage during
operation though nearly all within
prescribed safety limits and once you
move the detectors like a foot away from
the door the levels fall nearly to zero
even if there's like some food particle
or something caught in the door seal
now the industry will tell you that
there has never been any verified case
of human injury due to exposure from
radiation leakage from microwave ovens
this is from a guy at raytheon though
where the microwave oven was invented
after an engineer in a radar lab noticed
the chocolate bar in his pocket had
melted
there has been the rare case report of a
malfunctioning machine that didn't turn
off when the door was open and someone
burned themselves
but this was after her hand was in there
for like a full minute
raytheon engineers talk about how they
inadvertently exposed themselves lots of
times to open active microwaves they get
a a warm tummy they feel a little
transient warmth when they pass their
arm in and out of the oven but you know
no big deal they say
in fact the same microwaves used in
microwave ovens are the same used for
medical microwave diathermy
which physical therapists use like a hot
pack to treat like rotator cuff injuries
now
making the claim that well if the
medical profession uses it it must be
safe
isn't exactly the strongest argument but
does help to put things in perspective
when the heating of people is not
deliberate it may be desirable to limit
exposure
is that minor leakage during operation
anything to worry about though
in other words are there
non-thermal effects of microwaves if it
doesn't burn you can still hurt you
the soviets thought so irradiating
everyone in the u.s embassy in moscow
for decades
in terms of microwave ovens though the
only report i could find
was from over 40 years ago a case report
of a woman who developed cataracts after
using a leaky microwave oven
but that's all there was just this kind
of circumstantial evidence correlation
lots of people get cataracts lots of
people use microwaves there has to be
more than that
the only follow-up study i could find
was this turkish study published a few
decades later
but it was on rats
now they did end up finding some
superficial eye abnormalities on the
rats placed next to the microwave but
they were like right up against the door
and you know people don't tend to stick
their faces right up to the glass while
things are cooking so even if the same
thing happened to human eyes this study
might be of limited relevance but it
can't hurt to stand back from the
microwave while it's on
otherwise microwaves should be safe
unless
you drop it on your foot
[Music]
foreign